Programmer by day tester by night - what do I
really mean by that? Well, having looked at the
presentations that came before me, I think there
is a very logical connection to what some of the
people that are working on testing we're seeing
like Maurício and Manuel, but also to what Igor
was just saying about estimation, so let's dive
into the kitchen, because, actually, well if my
slides would move... I actually like to use the
kitchen as a parallel universe to the programming
universe that we're typically working in as
developers. So personally, I really love cooking,
and I like to make intricate dishes and - and put
them on the table, but as you can imagine, this
part of the work in the kitchen I don't typically
like that much. And I think a lot of people would
agree with me, that this is really what you try
to delay as much as possible, and well maybe you
have a dishwasher, and it's not too bad, but, well
it's definitely not my favorite part of the job.
So if I were to ask you, how much time does
making this beautiful dish really cost,
and maybe somebody would say 30 minutes, and if I
were to ask how much time you would spend on doing
the dishes, that would probably be considerably
longer than it takes you to cook. So from that
point of view, there is a message coming in so
i'm just going to see whether that's something
for me... No... So from that perspective,
we've been looking at how people perceive
the time taken to do tasks that you enjoy,
versus tasks that you might not enjoy so
much. There's actually a term for that that's
chronoception but also it's - it's kind of the
shortened form of the chrono-perception
the time it takes to do something.
And what we were really wondering in the
studies that we've done is, how do people look
at software testing, and how much time are they
spending on software testing. So my slides move -
we actually did - we created a tool a plug-in
for some popular development environments. We
unleashed that on 2442 developers from many
countries, but the key thing is that by having
this tool installed for several months, we were
able to collect 150 person-years of development
during the study. So this gives us a broad basis
to really look at how people are doing testing.
Now, during the installation we had this
fancy wizard and we were asking people,
do you do testing, do you do that in the
IDE, do you do other types of testing,
any other opinions that people might have on
testing. So one of the key questions was how
much time do you think you're spending time
on engineering test code versus engineering
what we call production code in the IDE. And the
answers - the average answer over all the 2443
developers that installed the tool was
about 50-50. So 49.5 percent of their time
was spent on engineering test code and
50.5 percent was spent on engineering
production code. Now there is something really
strange going on here, because there is this
really famous book - The Mythical Man Month from
Frederick Brooks - and in that book it's written
that testing takes approximately 50 percent of
our time. So it's actually very strange that the
book from - that was published at the end of the
1970s - actually premonitioned the results of this
first question in our study. So maybe there is
actually some folklore going on in our profession.
Now the key question obviously is that after
observing these developers, after minimally five
months and potentially even two years or more,
what would be the answer? How much time would
actually be spent on engineering test code? That
is dramatically different from the estimations.
One quarter of their time - of these developers
- was spent on engineering test code in the IDE
and 75 percent was spent on
engineering the production code.
Why is that? Well, these remain assumptions,
but the fact that software testing is really a
destructive activity, while engineering production
code is actually something that you bring to life,
something that you probably enjoy more, just
like the cooking versus doing the dishes,
could be a reason here why people
overestimate their testing efforts.
But there is more to this study because we also
looked at how people do test driven development,
and this really touches upon what Davide was
telling a few presentations before. So I think
we all know what test driven development is - it's
the core idea that you write your tests first and
then implement parts of the production code so
that your tests pass. And this really requires
this cycle where you have a failing test, you make
it pass, your refactor, and you continue doing
that. So from the 574 developers, which is like
just under 20 percent of the developers in our
study, that claimed to do TDD, there were actually
only 47 that really did TDD. Now you can say,
well, maybe they did it outside of the observation
- observation period, that could all well be,
but I think the key message here is that a lot
of people think they do it, but in practice
they don't do it that often. Because even for
those developers that we did observe that they
were doing TDD they only did it in very specific
cases, probably because it's not that easy to do.
So what does that really bring us to? Well,
the first takeaway is what developers think
they do or they estimate their efforts on, is
typically not what they really do in practice. So
the chronoception of software engineering tasks
is really something that we need to be careful
for. And secondly, maybe a plea is that we need to
understand software engineering tasks better: how
we do it, and also the effort that it takes to do
them. And we need to have better tools to estimate
how much time does it take to test,
how much time does it really take to
implement the feature. So my plea here is really
to also use software analytics during developments
to better understand what you and your team are
doing and also create more reliable estimations.
So finally the two takeaways of my talk:
the chrono perception - take into account
that certain things take more or less time
depending on certain factors in your personality.
And a general plea to do more software
analytics to become a better programmer. Thanks.